Hello again privacy fans!
Are you tired of initialising your Node manually
every time you start your computer?
Do you wish there was a hands off, easy solution
for restarting it when it fails?
Well, we've got good news for you, there is!
and in this short video we'll be explaining how.
So without any further ado, let's get into
it.
A service is a common way to describe a program
that runs in the background of any Operating System (OS).
Many programs run as services to make your
computer use simple and stress free, probably
without you even noticing.
Typically you will have something called a
service manager, which takes charge and deals
with these programs for you.
Today we'll be defining some rules which will
configure our service managers to both run
our Monero Nodes in the background every time
our PCs starts and restart them when they fail.
As usual, we will be covering Linux and Windows
separately, so please use the time stamps
in the description to get where you want to
be.
As Linux users, we often find that things
are slightly more complex and time consuming
to get set up.
But as always, there are advantages.
We will continue by assuming you followed
our video to set up your node.
If you already have your node set up via other
means, please check out our video to understand
how we approached things.
The first thing we’re going to do is change
the directory in which our **monerod** folder
is located.
At the moment it's located in the home directory
and we want it to be in the */opt/* directory.
*/opt/* aka “Option” or “Optional”,
is traditionally used to hold software and
programs which are run as an addition and
independently of anything else.
An advantage to using using this directory
is that changes require elevated privileges
and therefore cannot be altered easily.
To do this, we are going to use the *mv* command,
followed by the current directory and then
*/opt/*.
Now that's done, we’re going to create a
new user for our system called “monerod”.
Doing this means we can isolate the privileges
of the service to the working folder, which
is great for security amongst other things.
This next command will add the new user, create
a new user group under the same name and then
set the home directory to that which we just
created.
Next we will change the owner of the **monerod**
directory to match the username.
This will give the monerod user the correct
privileges to alter the files inside.
The command we'll be using to do with is `chown`
aka "change ownership" along with the R flag
so that it does this recursively for all the
subfolders.
The final command should look something like
this:
Finally we need to get on and specify the
service we will be creating.
Systemd is the name of the service manager
typically found in Linux distributions.
And it’s within the **library** directory
which we will need to place our config.
With your favourite text editor, you will
need to create a new file.
We’ll be using vim, and the following command:
We have already put together a template for
you to use, which can be found on our Github page.
Simply copy and paste it into the terminal
and your done!
As always, double check to make sure nothing
has been altered.
All that’s left to do is reload systemd,
enable our new service and then start it.
We can do that with the next three commands:
To check that everything is running smoothly
we can use the command `systemctl status monerod`.
If all is well, you should see that it is
Active and running.
Now every time you start your PC your node
will also be up and running and if it ever
fails, systemd will be there to restart it.
Remember, you can always check the logs in
the data directory for more detailed information.
Setting up your Windows service is quite simple
as its execution has been built into the daemon.
To install the daemon as a service, first
run Powershell "as administrator".
If you already have a node and used the default
directory, then you only need to add the "--install-service" flag.
If you followed our guide, or set your data
directory manually, you should also include
the "--data-dir" flag, followed by the correct
location.
Our command will look like this:
After pressing *enter* we can head to the
*Services* application in Windows where we'll
now find one called "Monero Daemon".
So that this service runs and restarts automatically,
we will need to edit the configuration slightly.
Right click on the service and select *Properties*.
First we want to change the startup type.
I'm going to select *Automatic*, with a delayed
start.
This way I know that essential services like
networking start ahead of it.
The next thing we want to turn our attention
to is the *recovery* tab.
Here we can tell Windows what to do if the
node fails for any reason.
For each failure, I want Windows to restart
the Monero Daemon so that it's up an running
as much as possible.
After making those changes, we can start the
process.
If you're already running the daemon, you
should stop it first.
Success!
Your Node should now be running as a Windows
service.
If you're interested to know the status of
your node you can also check the logs.
Our logs are located in the data directory.
If for whatever reason you are unable to access
your node, you should start with these.
Well there you have it.
Your node is now an integrated part of your
computing experience.
If you have any questions please let us know
either in the comments or through one of our
contact options on the about section of our
website.
If you found this useful and want to send
us a tip, our address can be found on screen now.
Well, that’s it from us, see you in the
next one.
~moneroguides